Register of the Brian Latell papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Brian Latell papers
1948-2008
2015C29
Hoover Institution Archives
29 manuscript boxes, 1 card file box (12.1 linear feet)
The Brian Latell papers primarily consist of research materials on Fidel Castro and Cuba. These contain a large chronological file comprised of English translations from the Cuban media and transcriptions of numerous speeches by Fidel Castro. Also included among the research materials are transcriptions and summaries of interviews with former Cuban officials and associates of Fidel and Raúl Castro. The interviews were conducted by Brian Latell and Adriana Bosch. Additionally, there is an extensive subject file that contains significant documentation on Fidel Castro and political developments in Cuba.
Latell, Brian.
Access
Box 30 closed until 2019 January 1. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
An American historian and a career CIA analyst, Brian Latell served as the agency's National Intelligence Officer for Latin America between 1990 and 1994. Later, he was a Professor of International Relations at Georgetown University and a Senior Research Associate at the Institute for Cuban and Cuban-American Studies at the University of Miami. Latell has published extensively on Cuba, Mexico, other Latin American subjects, and on foreign intelligence issues. He has written two books on Cuba and Fidel Castro, After Fidel: The Inside Story of Castro's Regime and Cuba's Next Leader (New York, 2005) and Castro's Secrets: The CIA and Cuba's Intelligence Machine (New York, 2012).
Scope and Contents note
The Brian Latell papers primarily consist of research materials on Fidel Castro and Cuba. These were compiled by Latell during his work as a CIA analyst on Cuba and were used as the basis of his books, After Fidel: The Inside Story of Castro's Regime and Castro's Secrets: The CIA and Cuba's Intelligence Machine. The research materials contain a large chronological file comprised of English translations from the Cuban media and transcriptions of numerous speeches by Fidel Castro. Also included among the research materials are transcriptions and summaries of interviews with former Cuban officials and associates of Fidel and Raúl Castro. The interviews were conducted by Brian Latell and Adriana Bosch. Additionally, there is an extensive subject file that contains significant documentation on Fidel Castro and political developments in Cuba. There is a small amount of correspondence and speeches and writings in the papers. The audiovisual materials include a number of videorecordings of programs about Fidel Castro and political events and social conditions in Cuba. The printed matter series contains a chronology, directories, a handbook, and reports, all relating to Cuba.
Castro, Fidel, 1926-; Cuba--Politics and government--1959-1990.; Cuba--Politics and government--1990-
- Biographical File, 1993-2000
  - Articles about Brian Latell, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Correspondence, 1986-2007
  - Amuchastegui, Domingo, 2002 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Beira, Mario L., 2007 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Betancourt, Ernesto F., 2001-2005 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Bush, Archer C., 2006 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Cannon, Angela, 2004 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Fuentes, Norberto, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Piñeiro y del Cueto, Carlos M., 1990 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Pino, Rafael de, 2005 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Romeu, Manuel E., 1986 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - San Martin, Nancy, 2004 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Whitaker, Kevin, 2004 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Whitehurst, Betty, 2004 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Speeches and Writings, 1985-2007
  - Notes on Raúl Castro, 1985 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Senate staff briefing, 2000 March 22 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "The United States and Cuba: Future Security Issues," Studies in Comparative International Development, 2000 Winter (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - "Castro and Crisis Management,", 2000 August 16 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - The Cuban Military and Transition Dynamics, 2003 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "A Revolution in Ruins," Washington Post, 2003 July 26 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Talk on the Cuban military, 2003 March 20 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "Raúl Castro: Confronting Fidel's Legacy in Cuba," Washington Quarterly, 2007 Summer (Box-folder 1: 21)
- Research Materials, 1948-2008
  - Chronological file relating to Fidel Castro and Cuba, 1959-2003
    Scope and Contents note
    Consists largely of translations from the Cuban media prepared by the Foreign Broadcast Information Service, a part of the Central Intelligence Agency's Directorate of Science and Technology.
    - 1959 (Box-folder 1: 22-23)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 1: 24-25)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 2: 1-9)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 3: 2-9)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 4: 1-7)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 5: 1-6)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 6: 1-5)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 6: 6-10)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 7: 1-5)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 7: 7-9)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 8: 1-5)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 8: 6-9)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 9: 1-4)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 9: 5-9)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 10: 4-7)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 10: 8-10)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 11: 1-4)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 11: 5-9)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 12: 4-10)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 13: 2-7)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 13: 8-10)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 14: 3-6)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 14: 7-10)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 15: 1-4)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 15: 5-7)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 15: 8-10)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 16: 1-3)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 16: 4-9)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 17: 1-5)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 17: 6-9)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 18: 1-6)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 18: 7-9)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 19: 3-6)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 19: 7-9)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 20: 1-5)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 20: 6-7)
    - 1995-1996 (Box-folder 20: 8)
    - 2001-2003 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - Interviews, 1986-2005
    - Conducted by Brian Latell, 1986-2005
      - Unidentified, 2004 (Box-folder 20: 10)
      - Abshire, Mike, 2000 (Box-folder 20: 11)
      - Amuchastegui, Domingo, 2004 (Box-folder 20: 12)
      - Benes, Bernardo, 2002 (Box-folder 20: 13)
      - Brugioni, Dino, 2002 (Box-folder 20: 14)
      - Carillo, Justo, 1986 (Box-folder 20: 15)
      - Castro, Juanita, 1986 (Box-folder 20: 16)
      - Corsell, Peter, 2005 (Box-folder 20: 17)
      - Costa, Jaime, 1986 (Box-folder 20: 18)
      - Cova, Tony de la, 2004 (Box-folder 20: 19)
      - Feliz, Padre, 1986 (Box-folder 20: 20)
      - Ferch, John, 2000 (Box-folder 20: 21)
      - Fernandez, Alina, 2004 (Box-folder 21: 1)
      - Fuentes, Norberto, 2004 (Box-folder 21: 2)
      - Gayol, Amado, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 3)
      - Grau, Juan, 2004 (Box-folder 21: 4)
      - Hidalgo, Alcibiades, 2005 (Box-folder 21: 5)
      - Llorente, Amando, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 6)
      - Matos, Huber, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 7)
      - McCaffrey, Barry, 2002 (Box-folder 21: 8)
      - Mestre, Ramón, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 9)
      - Moran Arce, Lucas, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 10)
      - Pino, Rafael del, 2005 (Box-folder 21: 11)
      - Pino Martinez, Fidel, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 13)
      - Post, Gerry, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 14)
      - Quevedo, Padre, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 15)
      - Rasco, Ignacio, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 16)
      - Rameu, Manuel, 1986 (Box-folder 21: 17)
      - Whitehurst, Betty, 2004 (Box-folder 21: 18)
    - Conducted by Adriana Bosch, 2003
      - Diaz Balart, Rafael, 2003 (Box-folder 21: 19)
      - Esquivel, Alfredo "El Chino,", 2003 (Box-folder 21: 20)
      - Fuentes, Norberto, 2003 (Box-folder 21: 21)
      - Rasco, José Ignacio, 2003 (Box-folder 21: 22)
  - Speeches, 1959-2004
    - Castro, Fidel, 1959-2004
      - Indexes, 1959-1981 (Box-folder 21: 23)
      - Summaries, 1970-1989
        - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 21: 24)
        - 1973-1984 (Box-folder 21: 25)
        - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 21: 26)
        - 1987-1989 (Box-folder 21: 27)
      - Transcripts, 1959-2004
        - 1959 (Box-folder 22: 1-3)
        - 1960 (Box-folder 22: 4)
        - 1975-2002 (Box-folder 22: 5)
        - 2004 (Box-folder 22: 6-7)
  - Subject file, 1948-2008
    - Arrufat, Antón, 1968 (Box-folder 22: 9)
    - Bayo, Alberto, 1960 (Box-folder 22: 10)
    - Castro family, 1957-2008
      - 1957-1965 (Box-folder 22: 11)
      - 1985-2008 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - Castro, Fidel, 1948-2002
      - 1948-1959 (Box-folder 23: 2)
      - 1959 (Box-folder 23: 3)
      - 1960-1963 (Box-folder 23: 4)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 23: 5)
      - 1970-1975 (Box-folder 23: 6)
      - 1981-1985 (Box-folder 23: 7)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 23: 8)
      - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 23: 9)
      - 1994-1999 (Box-folder 24: 1)
      - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 24: 2)
    - Castro, Raúl, 1958-2006
      - 1958-1965 (Box-folder 24: 3)
      - 1983-1986 (Box-folder 24: 4)
      - 2001-2006 (Box-folder 24: 5)
    - Cuba, 1957-2006
      - General, 2002 (Box-folder 24: 6)
      - Biological and chemical warfare, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 24: 7)
      - Military, 1980-2006
        - 1980-1986 (Box-folder 24: 8)
        - 1995 (Box-folder 24: 9-11)
        - 1999-2006 (Box-folder 24: 12)
      - Ochoa affair, 1984-1989
        - 1984-1989 (Box-folder 24: 13)
        - 1989 (Box-folder 24: 14)
      - Party and government leadership, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 25: 1)
      - Propaganda, 1964-1971
        - 1964 (Box-folder 25: 2)
        - 1965 (Box-folder 25: 3)
        - 1966 (Box-folder 25: 4)
        - 1967-1971 (Box-folder 25: 5)
      - Relations with the international community, 1995 (Box-folder 25: 6)
      - Relations with the Russian Federation, 1995 (Box-folder 25: 7)
      - Relations with the Union of Soviet Social Republic, 1984 (Box-folder 25: 8)
      - Relations with the United States, 1963-2002
        - 1963-1997 (Box-folder 25: 9)
        - 2002 (Box-folder 25: 10)
      - Revolution, 1957-1984
        - 1957-1971 (Box-folder 25: 11)
        - 1981-1984 (Box-folder 25: 12)
      - Terrorism, 1999-2003
        - 1999-2001 (Box-folder 25: 13)
        - 2001 (Box-folder 25: 14)
        - 2001-2003 (Box-folder 25: 15)
    - García Frías, Guillermo, 2006 (Box-folder 26: 1)
    - Guatemala, 1952-2007
      - 1952-1954 (Box-folder 26: 1)
      - 1954-1979 (Box-folder 26: 3)
      - 1997-2007 (Box-folder 26: 4)
    - Guevara, Ernesto "Che,", 1959-2004
      - 1959-1968 (Box-folder 26: 5)
      - 1975-2004 (Box-folder 26: 6)
    - Puerto Rico, 1975-2004
      - 1975 (Box-folder 26: 7)
      - 1979-1987 (Box-folder 26: 8)
      - 1999-2004 (Box-folder 26: 9)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1950-2002
  - Photograph of Fidel Pino Santos, 1960 (Box-folder 26: 10)
  - Videorecordings on VHS videocassettes, 1992-2002
    - "Deterioro de Fidel Castro,", undated (Box-folder 27: 1)
    - "Fidel,", undated (Box-folder 27: 2-3)
    - "Narcotráfico en Cuba,", undated (Box-folder 27: 4)
    - "CIA: The Secret Files," BBC television program, 1992 (Box-folder 27: 5-7)
    - Interview with Fidel Castro, ABC Prime Time Live, 1993 March 4 (Box-folder 27: 8)
    - U.S. Senate hearings on Cuba, 1993 July 29 (Box-folder 27: 9)
    - "Fidel Castro: El Comandante,", 1996 (Box-folder 27: 10)
    - "Cuba at the Crossroads," Center for Defense Information production, 1996 April 21 (Box-folder 27: 10)
    - "Ending the Cold War Freeze in Cuba," Center for Defense Information production, 1996 May 26 (Box-folder 27: 11)
    - "A 'Chernobyl' in Cuba?," Center for Defense Information production, 1998 February 15 (Box-folder 27: 12)
    - "Talking with Cuba," Center for Defense Information production, 1998 March 15 (Box-folder 27: 13)
    - "The Cuban Missile Crisis," History Channel program, 1998 October 24 (Box-folder 27: 14)
    - "Made in Cuba: Children of Paradise,", 2002 (Box-folder 27: 15)
- Printed Matter, 1968-1989
  - Chronology of events in Cuba, 1981 (Box-folder 28: 1)
  - Directories of Cuban officials, 1968-1987
    - 1968 (Box-folder 28: 2)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 28: 3)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 28: 4)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 28: 5)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 29: 1)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 29: 2)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 29: 3)
  - Handbook on the Cuban military, 1979 (Box-folder 29: 4)
  - Reports on Cuba, 1974-1989
    - 1974 (Box-folder 29: 5)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 29: 6)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 29: 7)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 29: 8)
- CLOSED (Box 30)